Catholic education is about the
salvation of the souls of the students
and also the souls of the teachers and
administrators. It's about the salvation
of souls. It's the mission of the church
to populate the kingdom of heaven with
people who are saved in Jesus Christ.
Everything else is downstream from that.
Whether it's learning math or learning
science or getting into a good college
or getting a good job, all of that is
far downstream from the goal in view
which is the salvation of souls. Okay.
To the degree that artificial
intelligence can serve as a positive
tool for that end of real authentic
Christian human formation, great. Where
it impedes that or or becomes part of
the mechanistic doway Prussian model of
just producing
factory bots, we should throw it out.
Well, Father Ambrose, uh, thank you so
much for joining us in the Gregorian
studio, uh, and being here for the
Builder's AI forum.
>> It's my pleasure. Thank you for the
invitation, Ben. I'm happy to be here.
Always happy to be in Rome and, uh,
happy to be speaking with you today.
>> Yeah. Know, we're we're very very um
blessed. And on on this first day here
at the forum, father, I wanted to I
wanted to to speak with you a little bit
about AI and education in particular and
to look at how um AI is accelerating
certain opportunities in the education
space and also kind of the problems that
you see in in your work uh in particular
with with the Everode institute.
>> My conffairs and I have developed an
online curriculum to teach the faith to
Catholic school teachers and
administrators. The Catholic school
system is kind of a disaster in America.
It needs renewal and one piece that
needs renewal is the catechetical
formation of the faculty and
administration. Okay. So that's what
we're working on. We use AI for that in
this way. We we've developed a online
platform.
My developers in fact the developer was
a cameraman who taught himself how to
code by using AI technology online right
now to build out a platform. Wow.
>> So that's a very practical immediate
technical use of AI that's been
extremely successful in my experience.
Now that's not in the classroom. That's
behind what's going on in the classroom.
my my team of lay people who help us
norbertines to film well create film and
then deploy our catechetical curriculum
use AI to help generate um texts
um scripts
I never use those just off the shelf as
it were from AI it always needs a human
touch but the team of people who help me
to do what I do best as a priest kind of
with the public face of this program.
They can line up for me the the working
materials from which I can then do my
priestly work. It's like a research tool
almost or um it's a Bible. It's a
library. I almost said bibloteka because
we're in Italy, but it's a library of a
sort that then I can reference
>> and then do my work. Okay. So, that's
been extremely helpful so far as a tool.
The
I see future possibilities in this. Uh,
for example, we've rolled out the
curriculum in an arch dascese that is
mostly English- speakaking but with a
heavily um heavy Spanish speaking
component. And so the teachers are
asking me, is this curriculum in
Spanish? And I tell them, well, no, but
within the next 12 months, I would like
to put the whole curriculum in Spanish.
And AI will help me to do that. Me and
my team, we'll be able to take all of
the filmed content as it is right now.
We can generate transcripts in all the
languages. But I'm interested to see how
AI technology can help us to refine,
hone, sharpen the instruments that we
already have created, if that makes
sense.
>> What do you think when you look at the
broader landscape in Catholic education
needs to change so that there there is
that proper formation where people know
what life is really truly about? Okay,
so that's a great question and actually
it's the intersection of where this
technology meets one of the big problems
which is a more theoretical problem with
ed education as such much of American
education I'd say all of western
education but obviously my experiences
in America as in the United States and
in Catholic schools also we have adopted
the doway model the dwey model of a very
utilitarian approach to education so you
get a good grade you get into a good
college, you get a good job so that you
can make a lot of money and rinse, wash
and repeat through the generations. This
is not human. This is capitalism. This
is the industrial revolution of the 19th
century and before philosophically
before applied to education. So that
it's a factory line production.
It reaches back to Prussia. It was a
military thing. You know, even the fact
that students sit in rows in seats,
>> I remember being too excited and having
trouble just focusing
>> all of this and the bell rings. All of
this is modeled on military formation so
that we can um deploy an army of
utilitarian bots in a capitalistic
culture for production. That's where it
comes from. It's not human.
So rethinking or re remembering what the
formation of the person is, what
Catholic education is, what education
is, you know, we can look all the way
back to the pre-Christian times of the
Greeks and the Romans about virtue. What
is virtue? What is what does it mean to
be a human being as such? And then how
do we form someone into the life where
they can be happy? A life of virtue. And
ultimately, of course, as Christians, we
know that means a life of grace,
sanctifying grace. We need to help
So this is all very I know this is very
high level. This is kind of 30,000 foot
theoretical conversation so far but I'm
going to make it practical. I'll try to
make it practical.
Education Catholic education is about
the salvation of the souls of the
students and also the souls of the
teachers and administrators. It's about
the salvation of souls. It's the mission
of the church to populate the kingdom of
heaven with people who are saved in
Jesus Christ.
Everything else is downstream from that.
Whether it's learning math or learning
science or getting into a good college
or getting a good job, all of that is
far downstream from the goal in view
which is the salvation of souls. Okay.
To the degree that artificial
intelligence can serve as a positive
tool for that end of real authentic
Christian human formation, great. where
it impedes that or or becomes part of
the mechanistic do-itian model of just
producing
factory bots, we should throw it out. So
I think that this is the role of
teachers in the classroom to say,
listen, we need to get it might be and
again I'm a kind of a purist about this.
I went to a liberal arts college. I was
trained by the Jesuits. I went to a
Jesuit boy school. I this and I'm a
middle-aged man. I grew up without any
of this stuff. And I think it's really
devastating for young people to be on a
screen all the time. I think that in an
ideal Catholic family, a a a child would
not even have a screen in front of him
or her
>> ever. Seriously, ever until maybe
they're 12 or 15. They would never have
an access to the internet or a cell
phone until they're 18. Now, is that
going to happen in North America?
Probably not.
So, but how can we avoid the dangers of
artificial intelligence and other
technologies that make that give us the
illusion of somehow knowing when in fact
we've just outboarded all of that
exploration and cognition and mental
exploration to a machine.
So that's a real ch that's a theoretical
challenge. And I think that the answer
to that comes down, Ben, to what is
artificial intelligence?
It's not ever going to be intelligence.
It will always be artificial
because intelligence is something that
requires a rational soul. Only humans
and angels and demons have such a soul.
So all of it is just simply an artifact.
It's a technological artifact and it
can't replace human intelligence. Does
that make sense?
>> But but father, what what do you what do
you say to that when when almost on some
level like the underlying principles of
this technology are embedded in in a
transhumanist ideology which is which is
of course the opposite on so many levels
to the faith or the or the the truths of
the faith.
I think that um well it means that we
have to be very circumspect and prudent
prudent about how we use it, how we
deploy it, knowing that this technology
is not necessarily
in its creation at the service of a
common good
and is it at the service of an an evil
end? I'm not convinced of that. I don't
know that it's it's just I think it's
morally neutral. Um, I was having a
conversation earlier today with somebody
who who was in Silicon Valley, very very
well placed in all of the big companies
that you would know from from Intel to
Microsoft to Amazon. and he was
describing how um the engineering
departments were you know creating all
of the algorithms that we all live with
um I'll just use one as an example that
you know the algorithms on let's say
something like Amazon or Amazon Prime
are designed specifically to capitalize
upon those people in the ecosystem who
are going to become addicted to the use
of this platform. So what does that
settle into? It settles into the people
who have the least amount of money but
the greatest propensity to spend on loan
to rack up debt and that's the
demographic that is most lucrative
>> which is of course not human at all in
fact abusive terrible
>> but the but the technology itself is not
concerned about that because what was
the motivation in creating it to
capitalize to algorithms AI generated
algorithms that cap that make it the the
bottom line the the supreme supreme end
and it doesn't matter who they're
stomping all over or ruining whose lives
they're ruining to get to that end.
Okay, so that means that we Catholics
and people who are thinking about these
and willing to use these technologies,
we can supply the proper end in view. We
can say okay listen the bottom line is
not the beall endall but the the the
common good of a culture or the
individual good of the soul concerned
the person concerned is more important
than the instrument instrumentalization
of that person for a capitalistic end or
some other end that would be just using
the person as an instrument.
>> We can provide that. Now, can we change
the can we inform the as you said the
transhuman motivation that is the very
origin of that? Maybe if we convince the
people the so-called Silicon Valley
giants who are really the the the
drivers of this movement. If we can
convince them that there's a higher good
than the bottom line.
Now, I mean, that's really what the
church has always been. We're we're
supposed to be a light in the world,
right? The church is the light. Christ
is the light of the world and we reflect
that light. Not everyone's going to see
it. And that means that we, like I said,
we have to be circumspect and prudent
about how we use a technology that is
going to be inclined to the instrument
in toward the instrumentalization of the
human person. What does that mean? Like
I said, I think for a family it means
probably don't give your child an iPhone
until they're 18. That's that seems to
me as a priest to be a very prudent
>> Yeah.
>> thing. Now then then of course I don't
have a family of my own. So I don't know
what that's like to have the 12-year-old
come home and say, "But all of my
friends have one." Then you of course
have the movement of families to say,
"Well, you know what? We probably
shouldn't have our kids in the public
school then." and probably not in the
Catholic school then either unless the
Catholic school is the kind that is on
board with that approach.
So then we think okay well are we going
to circle the wagon so much that our
children then don't engage with the
culture at all. Well no that's not
probably a good idea either. So
I'm highlighting for you Ben and for our
viewers and listeners
just how deeply we need to think about
the ramifications of the individual
choices we make in the application in
the use of these technologies.
It's important the these are important
decisions at every moment.
>> And I I guess father where where would
you draw the line in the classroom as as
well? I'm strongly against the
replacement of person-toperson education
in the classroom for education of
elementary school or high school or
probably even university. I think that
that's a bad idea to try to replace
real professors and teachers and you
know education is a leading it's it's to
lead out a ducate is to lead out out of
darkness into the into the light out of
ignorance into knowledge that requires a
human being who leads somebody who is
the teacher
almost like taking somebody by the hand
and bringing them come along with me I
want to show you what I know what I've
discovered let's go look for the truth
together. A machine can never be that.
Where could we use it? Well, like I
described in the work that I'm doing, I
think that we can use it as a tool to
help those people, those real human
people do their work. So, this program
that my convers
is, as I said, it's virtual. The
teachers either watch videos together as
a faculty and then discuss them or they
go home depending on their school and
they watch the videos and then they have
their assessment questions. Okay. So I'm
interested to see over the next 9 to 12
months how we can use AI technology as a
personal teaching agent personal
learning so that that teacher watches
the video and AI helps them helps us to
assess have they learned what they need
to learn from that video you know what
was important to you and then the AI can
they they type something in or speak
something back then the AI says okay
well did you think about this so and
that's I think that we are at a point
where the technology can do that
>> and that
without my being able to teach
personally
2500 educators across the country to be
sure that they watch that they heard
what I said or my confair said and
understood it. We can use AI technology
to do that. These are adults. These are
busy people and they're the ones who are
teaching the children. Now, would I I
would not want to replicate that in the
classroom for the 12-year-old or the
18-year-old or even for the 20-year-old,
but I think it's a tool that can help
>> at the back end to prepare the teacher.
>> It's very similar to, you know, I I
preach a lot. We priests have a lot of
work to do, but we have we have to be
able to access, let's say, I want to
know what St. John Chrysum says about
this passage of the scriptures. I can
use the computer for that. I can go back
to my my library shelf where I have St.
Thomas Aquinas's Katana Ala. It was a
technology from the 13th century where
he took the fathers, digested them
according to the gospels. So I can look
at this chapter and verse. St. Thomas
Aquinas did this for me. It's an AI
technology from the 13th century, right?
It's a tool
>> and I can pull that off my shelf and I
can look, okay, here's what St. John
Chrysm says in St. Augustine and you
know a kind of it's a
>> but it's material
>> and and it's of of great use to me in my
preaching and I can prepare my homaly
from that and I put the book back on the
shelf and then I preach
>> yes
>> I write the homaly I prepare the homaly
but I preach and that in the background
is a technology that's helped me I think
similarly like I just described the AI
engagement with the contents of the
Everode Institute curriculum can be that
for the teacher
They're learning the faith and then now
he or she tells the students who is
Jesus Christ, what is a sacrament, how
does the life of grace inform my work as
a biology teacher for the for the
freshman in high school. The AI is not
doing that. The teacher is doing that.
And our program assisted by AI at some
very minimal level right now, but it
could be more is helping the teacher to
be prepared well to do the teaching.
Does that make sense?
It's an instrument. It's a tool. It's a
sharp tool.
It can never replace the human.
>> I love that. And father, one final
question. Um, what are you most excited
about to get out of this uh edition of
the builder's AI form here in Rome? And
kind of a follow-up to that is what what
is giving you hope when you look at the
Catholic educational landscape in
general?
>> Okay, two good questions. A conference
like this is always an opportunity to
network with some of the people who are
doing the most good and who are the the
the sharpest instruments, the sharpest
tools in the in the tool box in God's
kingdom right now. Thinking very
creatively, working very hard. These are
the the movers and the shakers. And
that's really fun to be in a group of
people like that. and to have
conversations like this like we're
having right now or or hearing from
people in the conference contents but
especially in the networking that
happens around it to see where our
worlds intersect and where we can
support each other. I'm excited about
that. I always look forward to that in
this kind of a conference. It's my first
time at the builder's AI forum so far.
It's been a great day. I'm most the
other one was what am I excited about in
in Catholic education?
>> What gives you hope? Yeah.
>> Uh what gives me hope? This is going to
sound strange given that this is a
conversation about AI. What gives me
hope are those places like the
Chestertonmies,
the um classical um Catholic
startup schools very often outside of
the kind of on the periphery of ordinary
Catholic education
where
families, parents, teachers,
um and also sometimes clergy, but that's
usually not where the motivation comes
from, are throwing themselves into the
best of the old.
Why can we put a school together where
there is no screen? Where there's no
screen time?
>> That gives me hope. Is that weird for
AI?
>> I understand.
>> That gives me hope because I know that
those people will be the ones who will
understand how best to confront the
challenges when they come up against
them.
>> Beautiful. Well, Father Ambrose, thank
you so much for your time. This has been
wonderful. Thank you, Ben.